Hurry father, almost here. And I still haven't
selected my present and nothing is too good for
my little Adelaide, the daughter of the mayor of
Frieden and the richest and the most important
man as well. Oh, well, yes. Oh, good evening, Mr
Mayor Adelaide. Uh uh uh pastor, let me give you
a hand with that. Uh uh , thank you. Somehow, it
seems to get heavier every year. Uh Yes. Well,
the nativity scene is an important part of
our Christmas celebration and we all must do
our part. Even the mayor .Papa. Let's go. Yes, of
course, dear. Sorry. Pastor. That's all the help
I can be for now. I have a date with my favorite
daughter. I'm your only daughter, Papa. Yes. Well,
of course, that's right. Care for a paper this
evening. Mayor. It's a special edition only two
days to Christmas. You know. Thank you, Brigetta.
Christmas news is always good news. Uh Keep the
change. What I thank you, Mayor. It's got a bit
of the Christmas spirit yourself. I see. I suppose
I do. Brigetta, I suppose I do. Come father.
Good evening, Carla. Could you use a hand with
that? I surely could Brigetta. The village looks
wonderful. Everyone seems to be decorating this
year. Everyone except, ah, yes, poor, lonely Hans.
It's the same every year. Mhm Mhm... Good evening
Hans.Christmas is coming soon, or? Haven't you
noticed? The quicker it comes, the quicker it can
be over and done with? My goodness, Hans. I don't
understand why you hate Christmas so much? . and
I do not understand why you love Christmas
so much ? . So that makes us even. I love
everything about it. Lighting the advent candles,
the holiday food, the church celebrations,
the joyful Christmas spirit in the village. I even
love buying Christmas presents for my family. This
year. I'm buying my wife a warm winter coat
and my daughter has a list a mile long. Well,
I have no family.Don't you have something better
to do than to sit around here soaking up all my
heat. You do not have to be rude, Hans. I can
take a hint. It was not a hint. All right,
I'm leaving. I'm leaving. yeah.And what do you
want? Are you here for a Christmas handout too?
Well, do not bother Aldo Christmas is just another
excuse to be greedy and I will not be part of it.
What? Who is there? Care for a newspaper? Hans. I
have one left. Can you not see I have work to do.
I do not have time to read a newspaper. The bakery
has the most wonderful sweet cakes. You should buy
one to serve to your Christmas guests. You know,
as well as I do that. No one ever visits me. Not
now and certainly not at Christmas each year.
I keep hoping things will change for you. Hans.
I truly hope you have a Merry Christmas. Anyway.
What do you know? You're just a stupid bird. Now,
what, what do you want? Is that any way to greet
your mayor? Shoemaker? I'm very sorry, your honor.
I thought you were that old woman. What I did not
mean to say that you were an old woman. I mean,
you are certainly not old, never mind all that. We
are here on the most important business, Mr Mayor.
How may I be of service? I am searching for the
perfect Christmas gift for my darling Adelaide.
I doubt that we will find such a gift here, Papa.
Nevertheless, we must look at all possibilities.
Show us your finest ware shoemaker. I'm sorry, Mr
Mayor. But I've not made a new pair of shoes for
quite some time. Most of my business is repairing
old shoes for the people of the village. Come,
Papa. We're wasting our time here. You see, Aldo,
now, I have lost a sale. You are right. Aldo,
I should have offered to make a pair of shoes for
the mayor's daughter with that fine red leather I
have been saving, but it's too late now the mayor
will find his gift somewhere else. The mayor, he's
back, Mr Mayor. I am so glad you came back. Good
evening, Hans. Oh, it is only you, Gretchen. Yes,
it is only me. But today I have business for you.
What is this? Can you believe it? Hans. Someone
threw away these perfectly good shoes. These
shoes belong in the trash. They're hopeless. Oh,
I was hoping you could work your magic on them.
Oh, I want to have them cut down and repaired for
my granddaughter Elsa. They will be her Christmas
present. It would take no less than a miracle to
repair these shoes. But I can pay. pay.?? What
can you pay? Gretchen? .This is the finest bundle
I have. I was saving it for Elsa and myself, but
I would like you to have it. Twiggs won't buy my
supper. You know that please Hans. I know a bundle
of twigs is not much payment for your fine work,
but it is all I have and gift. I was hoping to
appeal to your Christmas spirit. Christmas spirit
more like greedy spirit. You mean everyone is so
worried about Christmas gifts. No one has ever
given me a gift and especially not at Christmas.
Hes I'm surprised at you. Christmas is about more
than presents. Not from what I see. Gifts at
Christmas are a symbol of the celebration of
God's great gift. See nothing but gifts but
Hans. God gave us the gift of his son Jesus
Christ. Born in Bethlehem to be the savior of
the world. Isn't that worth celebrating? Well,
yes but well, good night Hans. Hans, who are you?
What do you want? Do not be afraid I bring you
good news. This cannot be happening. Is this,
I mean, are you a real Hans? You can be happy
that Christmas is coming this year? Not you two.
This must be a nightmare for on this Christmas
you will receive a special gift. No one would
be silly enough to buy me a gift. I hate gifts.
This gift will be above all others. It will be a
gift from God. A gift from God to me. yeah.morning
Frederick. Good morning Brigetta. Where do they
sell the finest gifts in the village? I must buy a
present for someone very special. Well, how about
the bookbinder right across the street? Thank you,
Brigetta. Wonderful idea. Ah, good day Hans. How
nice to see you out and about. But what can I do
for you? I must have the very best gift in your
shop. Gustav. Oh, how about this lovely painting?
One of a kind, you know? No, no, no. It's nice.
But I must have your very best. This sculpture
is perfect. Seems to be real. Does it not? Oh,
I think I've seen it somewhere before. Don't you
have something different? Something beautiful? And
exciting and, and special come Hans. I have just
the thing, but that's just a simple box. You think
so? Watch this? It, it, it's amazing. Papa. Look,
Mr Mayor Adelaide. How lovely to see you, Gustav.
What is this? Why it is? That is my gift. Papa.
I want that music box. No, wait, I want to buy
it here, Gustav. You can have all of my money,
whatever he has. Gustav, I will pay more. But,
but sorry, Hans. Oh, Papa. How about one of
these other music boxes? Hans this one is nice.
You don't understand Gustav. It must be the very
best. I will keep looking. Please let me help
you with that. Gretchen. You like to exchange
gifts at Christmas, don't you? Yes. If they are
given in the right spirit. Well, what gift would
you give to someone very special? Oh, that depends
on who it is. Well, it is God actually. What would
you give to God for Christmas? I would give him
what I give him every day, my sins for his Pardon,
My weakness for his strength, my sorrow, for
his joy. Well, that is not exactly what I had
in mind. Think about it. Hans ponder it in your
heart. You will know what to do . Thank you,
Gretchen Elsa. You have saved the day. By the way,
Merry Christmas, Aldo my friend,I was hoping you
would come today. You're right. Aldo. It's been
too long since I've sung a Christmas song. I'll
tell you a little secret. I have forgotten some
of the words. But at Christmas, who cares just as
long as we sing. Take a look. My friend. This
is the finest leather in the land. I've saved
it for many years for just such an occasion. I
know it is small but it is the best. I will make
something wonderful with it. Silver nails, all
handmade by my father. And these silver bells
are from my very first Christmas tree. They make
me so happy. I'm making a gift. Aldo a Christmas
gift. I know what you're thinking. But I've been
told that this year I will receive a gift, a very
special gift and I must have one just as special
to give in return. I wonder what Hans is doing
in there. I hear he's making a gift for a king.
Oh, my a king. shhʃʃʃ . I am nearly finished. You
are so impatientnow. They are done. They're even
better than I'd hoped. I want everyone to see my
special gift. The red boots for Christmas. What,
what they are big. Make way, make way for the
mayor. Let me through. Please let me through.
Oh my.Those are the most beautiful boots I've
ever seen. That is the gift papa. That is what I
want for Christmas. The red boots. Yes, of course,
dear. Then you shall have them .shoemaker. Yes,
Mayor. How may I help you this fine Christmas
Eve? Oh, you are a sly one shoemaker. Christmas
Eve Indeed. I do not understand Mr Mayor. I have
not made a new pair of shoes for quite some
time. Mr Mayor, you knew I would not find a
gift as magnificent as these boots anywhere in
Frieden .uhh,. So you waited until Christmas Eve
to get the price up. So what is your price? I am
sorry, Mayor, but these boots are not for sale.
They are a gift. Of course, they are a gift, a
gift for my Adelaide. Now name your price. No,
the boots are not for sale. Not at any price. i
think i let the teapot boiling.This is not over
shoemaker.I mean to have those boots.I could not
giveup the red boot aldo.They are my gift to God.
Not yet aldo. these sweets cakes
are for my special visitor.
I must prepare them very best.
I dont not make our guest will mind,
if you have one piece of cake.
will you aldo?
soon aldo very soon.
its finally christmas eve.
we have everything ready.
it is time. oh its only
you fedric? I am happy to see you too hans.
I brought you a present. A christmas present.
Stamps? how useful.
Merry christmas hans.
You must be freezing. come in
and warm yourself with my fire.
I know I was little rough with you on other day.
I did not mean to be.
Oh my, my , you really have
got the christmas spirit hans.
Well actually i am expecting some one.
*knock on the door*
I brought you a present hans
tomorrow's christmas news paper.
Now you dont have to go out in cold to get one.
oh how nice thankyou.
Oh i wonder what smell is so delicious.
Christmas eve dinner i fixed it myself.
please, come in and join us.
here you sit down. be my guest.
its ok we have plenty.
come and join us hans.
I guess i will. its still early
my guest will arrive soon.
Guest? who your waiting for?
there he is.
dont go away
.you will be amazed.
Hans, merry christmas. i brought you a present.
one of my special calenders.Mayor, thankyou mayor
but its really not necessory.
About today well see just ...
you dont have to explain hans.
i know my adalin bit spoiled.
what iam I to do? she is my only daughter.
All i can offer you a christmas eve dinner.
well thankyou hans. i never
turn down the gift of meal.
Arn't you going to join us? some one
has to say for grace in it for dinner.
when i was a child, i used to
sing, a special grace on christmas.
Thanks for the wonderful meal hans. it
was the best i had for long time. it was
truely a special treat.it was delightful shoe
maker but i must run. i must get ready for mid
night service at the church you know?
I know, i really enjoyed your company.
No aldo i must have missed my special
gift.but it was a lovely evening after all.
go away aldo.
Oh its you again?
Have you come to tell more stories. i did not get
my special gift that you have promised. I have
everything ready, decorated, build a warm fire ,
cooked food and I have made red boot specially.
let me help you understand hans. giving gift on
christmas is a fine custom that you learnt from
your friends but the real message of christmas
is,God gift of his son born as baby in bethlahem.
for unto you is born this day on the city of
david as savior which is the christ the lord.
yes ,yes a savior which is christ the lord.
I understand now that was the real gift.
oh elsi my child.
Oh dady when you said you found my special
present i have no idea it would be the red boot.
pappa where is he going with my red boot?
wait adelaide.
dear child a christmas present.
I have received a wonderful gift from
God for this christmas aldo. this is
the least i can do. A blessed christmas
to you hans. thankyou, Merry christmas.
This is what christmas is all about adelaide.
we gift each other because God has given has
greatest gift for all.
Merry christmas.
இன்று கர்த்தராகிய கிறிஸ்து என்னும் இரட்சகர்
உங்களுக்குத் தாவீதின் ஊரிலே பிறந்திருக்கிறார்.