By wireless from the BBC,
her Majesty, the Queen
of the Netherlands.
Fellow Hollanders,
the lights have gone out
over free Holland.
Where only two weeks ago
there was a free nation
of men and women
brought up in the cherished tradition
of Christian civilization,
there is now the stillness of death.
Oppressed...
Threatened...
Watched on every side
by a power that would tear out
all hope from the soul of man.
The unhappy people of Holland
can only pray in silence.
For those who have lost their voice
but not their hope or their vision
in the struggle against the
onslaught of barbarism.
Long live the Netherlands!
Oh! Coffee...
In the parlor.
Achtung!
By order of the Reich's commissioner,
all citizens are ordered
to surrender their radios
and all other wireless equipment.
Achtung!
By order of the Reich's commissioner,
all citizens are ordered
to surrender their radios
and all other wireless equipment.
Good morning, Mr. Ten Boom.
I apologize for the intrusion.
They are collecting all radios.
I can see that.
Dutch policeman assisting them!
We do what we must.
All citizens are ordered
to surrender their radios
a radio, yes?
Upstairs...
In the parlor!
Get it.
You have many beautiful clocks here.
Bavarian?
The cabinet looks as if
it's a Berringer works.
Yeah, 1886.
You know watches...
Clocks?
My father is a watchmaker.
I grew up under his workbench.
And look what you've grown into.
What district?
Mattenbraw.
Ah, Mattenbraw...
Mattenbraw, 1895.
Magnificent.
But you should have seen
that watch when it came in.
The way some people treat a watch--
No care...
No...
Understanding.
It was a gift on my 70th birthday.
"To grandpa Ten Boom from
the children of Haarlem.
26th of March, 1931."
Give him the horn.
Any other radios in the house?
No! None!
Good day, then.
I don't want anything too expensive.
Then there's this one.
Seven jewels in a Swiss factory
but all the craftsmen
are German immigrants!
It's 42 Guilders.
It's for an anniversary.
We could spend a little more.
Well, there's this one...
Bamendor works.
Excuse me.
Papa, are you going out?
I will not dodder around this house
and do nothing.
Papa?
Excuse me...
I'm sorry.
Ah, yes...
You see, you could have it engraved
or you could order it in ah, a white gold.
The white gold is 60.
...Residing in the occupied Netherlands
must come forward according
to the following regulations.
A person is considered being.
Take your star.
...A Jew or part Jew
next.
If he has at least one grandparent
who is originally a full Jew.
A grandparent is considered a Jew
if he belongs or has belonged
to the Jewish church.
You shouldn't be here.
I've come for my star.
They are for Jews.
You don't have a "J" on your identity card.
You could get it for me.
If we all wear them,
they wouldn't know
the difference between a gentile and a Jew.
Go home please...
Go home.
I will wear my star!
And I won't take it off until
God tells me to take it off!
The God of Abraham and Isaac
and my God, too!
Whose leader?
Hurry, quick.
Turn around!
Good morning...
Isn't it Miss Ten Boom?
Children, stop.
The watchmaker's shop?
Ten Boom, Berteljorisstraat!
Yah! You came for our radio.
I wrote to my father.
I told him about your shop.
Who are those boys?
Why are they being allowed
to torment that man?
They are young Dutch patriots.
He was heard to make public statements
derogatory to the Reich and our Fuhrer.
They are expressing their indignation.
Patriots?
Who are these children?
I teach a class.
I tell them about God.
At least, I used to.
This will be the last one.
Thanks to your new directive
concerning unauthorized meetings.
Miss Ten Boom...
The measures are temporary.
Once all this is over,
when order has been restored,
then all the Aryan peoples will live together
as brothers in our Reich.
Men live together as brothers
only in the kingdom of our Lord.
Nowhere else.
May we go?
Come...
Yeah.
Children...
Come! Come!
Some cookies.
Ah, yeah,
Jan comes running for the cookies.
Lisa, yeah.
Arnold...
Oh yeah!
Ha! Cookies?
Aha!
I...I may not be able to
be with you for a while.
Yes?
Ahh...
But Jesus will still be there...
Always watching over you.
You see...
Without Jesus,
we are like this...
Empty!
We can do nothing.
But then Jesus fills us with His love.
Then we are full...
Yeah!
We can do anything...
We can do anything!
Nothing serious, pastor.
A little bit dirt maybe.
It's been losing 5 seconds a day.
Maybe a good cleaning
um-hum...
You can do it now?
While I'm here...
It really would be most helpful.
Yeah!
Good!
I'll go up and have a chat with your papa.
I hear he's been wearing a Jewish star.
Stubbornness is the child of pride
and pride is the first of
the seven deadly sins.
I'll speak to him about it.
Oh, I need to the back
at the church by 1:30.
It will be ready.
Dr. Heemstra!
Miss Ten Boom.
I can only stay for a moment.
Oh...
Oh!
Oh, we need milk for him, not soup.
Good Lord,
you don't intend to keep it.
But you can't!!
It's illegal!
You could all be arrested.
He's beautiful.
Pastor...
The Lord must have sent you here.
You live in the country.
Nothing could be safer.
It's...
Impossible.
I-I...
Have my own family to think of.
We could lose everything for that child.
Where would my church be
w-without a Shepherd.
Oh, but...
No, Betsie!
The pastor has decided.
It is the law!
And Christians must obey the law!
Think what you are risking
for the sake of one Jewish baby.
Will you report us pastor,
if the baby must stay a while with us?
Corrie...
We are meant to obey the law of the state,
if it does not go against
a higher law of God.
Pastor, you want me to take off my star.
Very well, I will not wear it.
And we will keep the child!
As a Christian...
I am sorry that any man must suffer
no matter who he is...
Or what his race.
But remember, it is the Jews.
Who gave us the Bible.
And our Savior!
It is on your heads.
I'll pick up my watch tomorrow.
Good day, Ten Boom.
Ladies.
God forgive him.
He did not mean it.
How can that man call
himself a Christian?
If a mouse lives in the cookie jar,
that doesn't necessarily
make him a cookie.
What will we do?
We must have milk.
He should go to the country.
Careful, he'll suffocate.
Where will you send him?
God will know.
Doors are opening all over Holland.
Last week we had a Dutch farm girl
and a Prussian Baroness
in the same bed.
And now you'll have a
little Moses in the basket.
Corrie, please.
Thank you.
Willem!
He must not cry!
You certainly are organized.
Oh, it's not the first time.
We are a way station...
For a day or for a week.
You've kept this from us, Willem?
German Jews before the
occupation and now the Dutch.
We do what we can
but the Nazis will not be satisfied
until there's not a Jew left in Europe.
They have touched the apple of God's eye.
I pity them!
I hate them.
Oh, Corrie...
You can't hate anyone
and walk with the Lord.
You could have told us,
Willem, we might have helped.
The important thing is to get
our little friend out of here.
You'd be hard pressed to explain
a sudden gift from heaven.
Son, I'll walk with you a little way.
Goodbye, Moses.
We've been managing all right
some potatoes...
And occasionally eggs, even!
So far we haven't done too badly.
And of course we...
Is this the Dutch farm girl?
Grandpa!
Kik, did you get anything?
The carbon from the wastebasket--
if you hold it up to the light,
you can just make it out.
Thank you.
You see, papa,
we have a contact in the Gestapo office.
Hush!!
He gives us the deportation
lists whenever he can.
All right, Kik!
Uh-huh.
Good-bye, grandpa.
God bless you, Kik.
Steady it with one hand...
Good!
Papa...
Every day now...
They send 400 Jews from
Amsterdam Central Station.
We reach those we can.
Do we know anyone on the list?
Gewassen!
Steinweinen!
Schloss! Schloss!
I beg your pardon.
No, please,
I...
I'm sorry...
To...
To inconvenience you.
Maybe he's a...
Papa...
There's a gentleman upstairs.
We have met.
Well, it was so late...
He had no place to go
papa, he's a professor.
Willem studied with him.
They've closed the university.
All the Jewish teachers were forced...
Ah, Betsie...
Good morning again, professor.
I apologize for the
intrusion Mr Ten Boom.
Please...
Thank you.
Professor...
Will you do us the honor
of asking the blessing?
Blessed art thou, oh Lord, our God,
who bringest forth bread from the earth.
Amen.
Ah! How fortunate aunt bep had big feet.
Yes.
Hm...
Oh...
Now, when were you born?
Born?
Ummm.
Oh...
Ah, 19th August, 1885.
Father's name?
Ten Boom, Casper.
Mother?
Ten Boom, Cornelia.
Her maiden name?
Miss Ten Boom,
if we are stopped, I...
I could never pass as you.
Professor Ziener...
There are no "ifs" in God's world.
Now, he brought you to this house,
and he will see you get safely away.
This is where we turn, professor.
Stay close with me.
I'll try.
It's wonderful professor!
We're almost there.
Katrien.
Aunt Corrie!
Aunt Corrie. Katrien,
I need your father's help.
You should have seen professor
Ziener getting into the boat.
Katrien's father attending
him like he was
Queen Wilhelmina boarding the yacht!
Cornelia, do you think we are
enjoying this a little too much?
Enjoying?
No, I was terrified.
If I hadn't been able to laugh at him
all dressed up like Betsie
Oh! Thank God.
He kept the patrols away.
Be sure to save a piece of
cake for Willem's friend.
Friend?
It's all very mysterious.
Someone he wants us to meet.
What did Willem say when you
told him about professor Ziener?
This is not some game you
play when the mood strikes.
If you become involved in this work,
people will be forced to trust you...
With their lives!
I told you, Willem.
We gave him my papers.
We thought it out very carefully.
And if they questioned him...
Was he supposed to sing soprano?
No...He was going to have...
Quincy throat.
Excuse me.
You wander along the canal
picking someone out of thin air
how did you know you could trust him?
I knew the man.
And I knew what the Lord had told me.
Papa...
You are the master of this house.
The master of this house...
Commands that we open the door
to anyone who knocks.
We cannot afford to ignore anyone
who seriously engages in our
work, whatever their methods.
Perhaps you will allow us to...
assist your efforts.
Thank you for the delivery, Mr. Smit.
Only for emergencies!
We have a contact at the exchange,
but you can never be certain
that the line is not tapped.
But you will be expected to
develop your own sources.
The less contact you have with me,
or with anyone else...
the better.
Willem, we know half of Haarlem.
We have friends everywhere!
Dear lady,
knowing them is one thing...
Knowing their political views...
God knows!
And we will ask him to lead.
Oh, we appreciate your concern,
Mr. Sluring.
We are not the most likely candidates.
But since there is a need.
We must do what we can to meet it.
People have every kind of reason
for wanting to work in the underground
excitement, perhaps.
Mr. Sluring,
we are past the age when excitement is
of any major concern in our lives.
Truthfully...
I'd rather do anything else.
I'd like to close the door
and never open it again
until this whole hideous thing is over.
But, that's me.
My Lord Jesus tells me
to open the door to whatever comes.
To give his love in whatever way I can.
And I will listen to his voice...
Not mine.
Do we pass inspection?
How many can you take?
There's ah, mama's room
and there's your old room,
and there's aunt Anna's room
and auntie Bep's room,
and our 3 rooms--
that's 7.
And we can share a bed if we have to.
So! Our hotel is ready for guests.
Not quite.
What do you do if the Gestapo comes?
You will have a visitor,
a Jan Smit.
Actually, it's two houses.
Over a hundred years ago
they were joined together.
The one in the front is 2 rooms deep
and one room wide.
The one at the back,
here, is 3 rooms:
One on top of the other.
Papa!
This is Mr. Smit.
Mr. Smit.
I know some Smits in Amsterdam.
Are you with the Smit family
that makes the candy?
Father, this is the man
that I told you about.
He's come to inspect the house.
Oh! A building inspector?
Do you have the offices
on Grote Hous Street?
No, papa.
He is not a building inspector,
and his name is not Smit.
Not Smit?
Excuse us, papa.
We must look at the rest of the house.
The parlor...
Mealtimes--
that's a favorite hour for a raid.
Watch your wastebaskets...
and ashtrays.
We need to be as high as possible.
It allows for the best
chance to reach a safe place
while they search below.
These are all bedrooms?
Yeah.
If a raid comes at night,
they'll have to take their bedding,
but make certain the mattress gets turned.
A favorite trick of the Gestapo
feeling for a warm spot on the bed.
What's up there?
Ah-ha!
The roof is directly above.
Who sleeps here?
I do.
Perfect!!
The wall...
Will go... Here!
All clear! The sign's in the window.
You see, there is a distinctive marking--
you can always tell Flenstadht work.
Peter!
Lovely day, aunt Betsie.
Peter! No, no.
I'll come for it Tuesday then.
Good.
Ah! Herr Ten Boom!
Friessian!
Such beautiful wood!
My father made a case like this once.
Oh, he spent months building it,
polishing... oiling.
It ah...
Is just a shell...
It needs a complete set of works.
What price will you be asking?
Well, it will take some
months to be ready.
Name a good price.
Exorbitant, even,
I'll pay.
I like the clock.
I can afford the best!
But it, it has no works.
None.
Very well.
Tuesday, Herr Ten Boom.
Kik! Hurry!
Aunt Betsie,
how many times do you have to be told
take the sign out of the window
when it isn't safe!!
Oh, Kik, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry!!
Grandpa...
Look!
Tea, Mr. Smit?
Oh! Danke!
Yes, yes, yes, yes!
Good morning.
Milk! Where did you get...
Not milk...
Paint!
Paint?
Betsie!
Oh, Betsie.
Do you remember Fred Koonstra?
Of course...
He read our electric meter for years.
His daughter was in our Bible class.
Yeah!...
Milk!!!
Paint.
Paint! Elsie Koonstra.
I know her name.
I just had to sort out a few faces.
She must be in her twenties by now.
I heard yesterday that Fred Koonstra
works at the food office.
Where?
They issue ration cards.
I will be frank.
We've had some unexpected company.
First, a baby...
Then a man...
And now last night, a couple.
All Jews, Mr. Koonstra.
Why do you tell me?
There are only three of
us left at home now--
my father, my sister, and me,
and our ration cards are just not enough.
All ration cards are checked.
Accounted for in a dozen different ways.
Yeah! Yeah! I...
I know.
I...
I should not have asked you.
I thought perhaps you could advise me.
The food office at Utrecht
was robbed last week.
The men were caught
...and shot.
If it happened at noon,
when just the record clerk
and I were there...
We'd have to be tied and gagged.
How many cards do you need?
A hundred!
I know someone who might do it.
Papa! Now!!
Papa!
Done.
How long?
47 seconds!
They better not send us
anyone wider than me.
Hallelujah!
Our Lord, we ask your blessing
on this hiding place.
You eat what you like!
Herren, it is not Kosher.
It's not important.
Would you pass the potatoes, please?
Go, go! Go!
Hurry, hurry.
...One at the head, one at the foot,
one on each side.
You're spilling it!
One minute and 15 seconds.
Ah! It's long enough
to curdle the stomach.
Peace be with this house
and all that dwell within it.
The peace of the Lord God...
Get inside!
You stand outside and pray.
I was told you had accommodations.
I will require a room to myself
quiet for study, preferably
with no children.
Well, can you take me in?
Well, yes...
Good.
...I suppose so, but there
are many questions that I...
I would like something to eat.
The last meal was yesterday--
thank you-- at noon.
This is a Kosher house?
Well, we try.
We have many requests that
we're not able to fill.
There are no children?
Well, not at present,
but they come and they go.
Let them stay gone while I am here.
This the way?
Yeah! But I would first like
to talk to you about...
My contacts have told me that
most of your quests are transient
they are on their way out of the country.
Most of them, yes.
Well, I will not be.
I'm a teacher and chief cantor for
the congregation Beth Kodesh.
I will not be driven away by
these grinning Siegfreids
and their thousand-year Reich.
Who is this man?...
A partriarch like Isaac
or Jacob, father of nations.
Papa, we have a new guest.
This is my father, Mr. Ten Boom.
Papa, this is Mr...
Wijnstok, Meyer Wijnstok.
Pleased to meet you Ten Boom.
God willing and the
accommodations proving suitable,
I will be staying with you
until this nonsense is over.
You are welcome.
Thank you.
Miss Ten Boom, my room please.
Aunt Betsie!
Ohh!!
My friend Jan needs a
place to stay for awhile.
Oh!
He got away from the transport.
By noon tomorrow he will
have new identity papers.
But...
Where did you get the uniforms?
Not all Germans are Nazis, aunt Betsie.
Is it Jan?
Corrie! Mr. Wijnstok refused
kitchen duty again.
He has to study.
He wants to eat, he's got to
do his share of the work.
Where is he now?
In the parlor.
Oh can I have...
Oh, excuse me.
It's all right.
Corrie, he's already been upset today.
He found out we call him
"Eusie" behind his back.
Maybe it's his great dignity.
He should be flattered he
reminds us of a scholar!
But a gentile scholar.
He said, "We should have at
least called him Josephus."
Rules are rules!
Mr. Wijnstok, my sister tells
me that you have refused...
Miss Ten Boom, I am praying.
First you refused to work on Saturday,
because that was the Sabbath.
Then you refused to work on Sunday
because that was our day of rest.
I was simply trying to pay respect
to the practice of this house.
But today is Tuesday.
Tell me, Miss Ten Boom,
why you have found it necessary
to give me a nickname?
We have called you Eusie simply because...
Eusie is the kind of a name
you would give to a pet cat.
As a guest in your house,
am I no longer entitled to respect?
We are getting completely off the subject.
However, as it seems to
give you both satisfaction,
please have the courage to
use the name to my face.
If you want Eusie,
Eusie it will be.
Ladies!
Get up!
Ah, good morning!
Good morning!
Morning.
It's after seven.
Can't you smell breakfast?
Yeah!
Betsie!
Betsie...
Oh, good morning!
What is it?
Today is the 18th!
It's mama and papa's anniversary!
Oh, no.
54 coupons for cream puffs.
Tell Mr. Klassen it's for papa.
Corrie...
That blouse and that skirt...
You just can't.
Not today.
But...
You'd look like a flag on a mudboat.
But you always liked this blouse.
The blouse is beautiful
and you are beautiful,
but the combination of you,
the blouse, and the skirt is impossible.
Huh.
♪San-ta Lu-ci-a ♪
♪ Santa... Luci...a ♪
Papa Ten Boom,
you are a most singular man.
For such a great man,
there must have been a great woman.
Now this is not exactly a song,
it's more a...
Um, a blessing.
It's, ah...
It means "May God bless you,
may he protect you,
and may his face shine upon you."
Do you want the whole
of Haarlem to hear you?
I did not ask to be born a Jew.
I am sick of being expected to
bear the burden of suffering
for the entire world
because my mother's name was
...Stein.
So, you will be another Esau,
selling your birthright
for a mess of porridge!!
I don't want your great Judaic heritage!
I don't want any part of
your Lord God Jehovah.
It is no easy thing
to stand in the palm of God's hand.
Betsie, go get the door.
Betsie, go!!
Yes, yes I go.
Oh...
Um...
Yes, in a moment!!
It's Mrs. Beukers.
Oh!!
Betsie, are you crazy?
The whole street can
hear your Jews singing.
Thank you.
Tonight on the overseas service of the BBC,
we have special greetings and love to 2017,
...Private Sidney Harris from his mother.
And to 1433,
Lance corporal Phillip Munen
from his wife, Doris.
Double three.
Has anyone seen or heard of Alan Stokes
who was last heard of in Bournmouth?
His father is in the hospital
in London and dangerously ill.
Will Alan Stokes please contact
guys hospital Whitehall 9527.
9527.
That number again is Whitehall 9527.
2-7.
The next program is music played by...
How can I ever remember them?
The way we used to pass
messages in church.
Kik.
Aunt Corrie.
All these numbers...
What do they mean?
Oh, different things,
instructions mostly.
Instructions for what?
Well, there could be a
pilot down somewhere.
The numbers could be coordinates
for picking him up...
Or maybe for blowing up
a Nazi supply train!
Things like that.
Sabotage?
We could have blood on our hands.
For Holland.
Does that make it right?
Lying, stealing, killing?
Whatever helps Holland is right.
I need the message aunt Corrie,
they're waiting.
What will we be like when this is over?
Miss Ten Boom?
Yeah!
Thank you for being so prompt.
I have heard a great deal about you...
About your work.
I'm afraid it's my father's work.
Not the watchmaking.
Your other work.
You mean with the children?
We've had to disband the class.
Miss Ten Boom,
many of us who are in no position
to publicize our feelings,
are in great sympathy
with what you're doing.
People call your house
"God's underground."
Are you trying to trap me, sir?
Using the name of the
Lord is not the way.
If it were a trap,
you would be down the hall
talking with the Gestapo.
This will go no further.
Then why did you send for me?
I want you...
To pass this man's name
on to your friends.
Who is he?
A businessman.
He betrays people to the Gestapo.
The going rate is 75 Guilders a head.
Just pass it along...
They'll take care of him.
If I could do what you ask,
it would be the same
as killing him myself.
I can only put him in
the hands of the Lord,
and ask the Lord to reach his heart.
You do that, Miss Ten Boom.
The demons are out tonight.
I would assume you could
sleep through anything.
Some tea?
Thank you.
You know, Miss Ten Boom,
you and I are very much alike.
Stubborn...Tough... Determined.
You still don't do your share of the work.
We are the same, yes.
But I am more so...
So...
I win!
Did you know that...
I have a wife and small son?
Precisely--
I do not choose to expose myself.
They got away.
At least I...
Think they did.
I will not go around like the others,
begging for sympathy and reassurance.
We know so little about each other.
You busy yourself with our needs.
Surely you have some needs of your own.
It's people like us,
Miss Ten Boom...
Raging torrents behind the stubborn jaw.
No torrents.
You might say my life has been...
Boring.
Until all this?
Until all this.
Was marriage never considered
for the daughters Ten Boom?
Betsie was always unwell.
She was told she could
not bear children,
so she chose not to marry.
And you?
I had a young man,
But I was not cut from fine
enough cloth for his family.
I lacked grace.
Still...
I was the first woman
to be licensed a
watchmaker in Holland.
And you have your father,
and you have your religion.
Is it enough?
More than enough.
God has been good to me.
Yes, I...
I think he has.
And I think I shall be
going back to my bed.
I will pray for your family.
Don't think you will get me to
peel potatoes, Miss Ten Boom.
Good morning.
Miss Ten Boom?
Yeah?
My name is Vogel...
Jan Vogel.
I came all the way from Ermelo.
Do you have a watch that needs repair?
I need 600 Guilders.
I've heard you have certain contacts.
I don't understand.
It's my wife...
She's been arrested.
She's Jewish.
That's a lot of money.
There's a policeman who'll arrange
everything for 600 Guilders...
And then she'll need a place to hide.
What now?
Somebody's calling for this within the hour.
A Mr. Jan Vogel.
He's from Ermelo.
His wife's been taken.
It's for a bribe.
Oh...
You are impossible.
Now here...
I'll take care of it.
Now will you please go to bed.
But Willem and Tine are coming.
You can come down later.
Be sure and call me.
I will.
And use the steam kettle!
Yeah, yeah.
I thought that today
the Lord would have
us read from Romans,
Chapter 8.
"What then can separate
us from Christ's love?
Can hardship or calamity?
Can persecution or abuse?
If we are hungry or poor,
or in danger, or threatened with death.
Does that mean that God has deserted us?
No! Despite all this,
we have overwhelming victory
through Christ who loves us.
For I am convinced that neither death
nor life nor the powers of Heaven,
nor the powers of Hell itself
can keep God's love from us.
Nothing in the world as it is...
Or the world as it shall be,
in the forces of the universe.
...In all creation will
ever be able to separate us.
Around the side door.
Come on!
Get upstairs.
Corrie!
Yes, I'm sorry we're closed until 2:00.
Miss Ten Boom, I...
I have an appointment with your sister.
Mr. Ah, Vogel?
I need the money.
Now!
Yes, of course, I'll get it.
Please, Miss Ten Boom!
Places, everyone!
Come on, hurry!
Please, Miss Ten Boom!!!
Yes, yes in a moment!!!
I'm just collecting it!
Oh!!!
Stay here!
I'll take the top.
Miss Ten Boom?
Ten Boom...
Elizabeth.
Where do you hide your ration cards?
I don't know what you're talking about.
No!!!!
Where are the Jews?
What Jews?
Oh! Lord Jesus, help me!
Aaahhhh.
Where are the Jews?
No, please.
Where is the secret room?
Corrie!
This must stop!!
There's been no wrong done in this house.
Then what are you doing with
all these ration cards,
feeding an army?
What does it say in that book of yours
about obeying the government?
Hum?
There comes a time...
When we must choose
between God and man.
Halt!!!!
Keep moving.
Nam, bitte?
Cornelia...
Ten Boom.
Elizabeth.
Your name?
Ten Boom, Casper.
Papa!
Only six?
Seven...
God is with us.
Ten Boom...
Give me your word you
will behave yourself,
and you can die in your bed, old man,
where you belong.
If I stay behind,
I will open my door to
anyone who knocks for help.
Close it up.
Seal the house.
Clear the trucks!
Out! Out!
Out!!!
Corrie, take my hand.
My sister, she needs a doctor.
Move on!!
Papa! Papa!!!
God be with you papa!!
And with you, my daughters.
I have to get in there.
Fever down?
You had them worried...
Typhus.
Yesterday's rations,
I saved them for you.
Listen, I have family here.
My sister, my brother,
my father, my nephew--
the Ten Boom family.
Can you find out where they are?
Ssssshh!
Maybe, listen...
I can get soap,
Aspirin, cigarettes.
You can pay me when you
start getting mail.
Soap, 25 Guilders;
Aspirin, 50; Cigarettes, 100.
Most anything!
Can you get me a Bible?
It's Kik! It's safe now.
Oh, thank God!
Ssh! On the roof quickly.
The roof!
Where are your family?
Hurry!
The Ten Booms?
Still in prison.
That's all we know.
Mama made the coverlet on my bed...
It was in her trousseau.
The painting by the mirror is a...
Do not go!
Stay...
Please.
They think I have to feed you.
Everybody's been released.
Everybody?
Except your sister Betsie,
and your father, too, I think--
I'm not sure.
Oh, thank you, Lord!
Oh Lord, thank you!
Here's your bread from the warden's bakery...
Fresh!
Oh, Lord...
You have done wonders.
Don't I get a little credit.
Lord, bless this angel.
Bless you!
Do you think
you can last here doing that?
Praying?
The only way to live here...
Is to hate.
Hate can put you in a
worse prison than this.
I have been 3 years in this hole.
I worked my way to a position.
And I live to get the
swine who betrayed me.
Now that's 75 Guilders!
Are you cold?
It seems reasonably pleasant.
I'm sorry.
Now you're here for violation
of the rationing rules.
Would you mind telling me
where you got these extra ration cards?
Sometimes they just appeared.
What do you mean...
appeared?
Pushed under the door.
Sometimes they were handed
to me in the market.
By whom?
A Mr. Smit.
Mr. Jan Smit?
Will you tell me about your other activities?
My sister and I held Bible classes,
until such meetings were forbidden.
And we worked with retarded children.
How?
Excuse me?
How would you work with them?
We taught them about God.
What a waste.
If you wanted converts,
surely one normal person is worth
all the half-wits in the world.
In the eyes of God,
one simple child may be
worth more than...
... a watchmaker's daughter.
Perhaps...
But I know he keeps me
always in his sight.
You actually believe that?
I believe that you are in
his sight too, lieutenant.
Tell me, Miss Ten Boom,
how can you believe in a God
who lets an old man die in prison?
His body forgotten somewhere
in a pauper's grave.
My father?
I understand he was taken
ill after about 10 days.
He was taken to a hospital in the Haag,
unfortunately, there were no beds available.
He seemingly died in the hallway.
Some failure of organization.
Under such circumstances where
no one claims the body,
it is difficult to trace.
I know where my father is, lieutenant.
That will be all, Miss Ten Boom.
Oh, you have news from home.
Papa...
Papa.
Snell, snell, snell!!
Snell, snell.
Betsie!! Betsie!!
Corrie, oh!!!!
It's my sister!
Betsie!
Betsie!!!!
Corrie!!!!
Snell!!! Snell!!
Snell!
Nobody is permitted to keep
any personal possession.
There will be no exceptions.
Remove your clothes...
I can't!
They're taking everything.
What he's asked us to do,
he'll help us to do.
Do you want us to die for a little skin?
I can't.
There will be no exceptions.
Where are you going?
Toilets, please!
Showers--
use the drain holes.
Please understand,
she's been very ill.
Name?
Bridget Marie.
Priest, Frances.
Quick, take off your sweater.
Hurry!
They'll send us back here after we shower.
I can't!
Yes, yes, you can. Hurry!
Danke!
I got my shoes!
How much for underwear?
A week's bread ration.
Next!
Next!!
Oh, Lord...
You have given us your word
and hidden it through everything!
Now open up a way for us to get
it through the gates of Hell.
Achtung!
It's in God's hands now.
Next.
Name?
De Greuth, Alisa!
Classification.
Political.
Next.
Next!!!
Name!!
Yedmuelle, Grace.
Classification?
Criminal.
Next!
Ten Boom, Elizabeth.
Classification?
Ah, political.
Next!!
Ten Boom, Cornelia.
Classification?
Political.
Next.
Next!!!
Berte, Liza.
Classification.
Political.
Next!
Classification.
Ten Boom, over here!
The hell you do!
Fleas!
Lice!
Can you imagine what mama would say?
Achtung!
Ravensbruck is not a rest camp.
Roll call, 4:30 every morning.
...7 days a week.
Tomorrow, assignment to work details.
Those who cannot work
report to sick call...
and they better be sick!
You will receive 1/2 pound of bread
and 1/2 liter of soup per day.
One small observation upon
which your life depends--
there is only one road to freedom...
Work!
Get it up!
Hoist it.
Snell!.
Snell!!
You are Dutch?
Some of my people are Dutch...
On my mother's side.
You are not the only one
surprised to be here.
I thought I would be working
at a relocation center...
Refugees.
The supplies are extremely limited.
An accurate record is essential
I know my way around hospitals,
I was kind of nurse once.
I assume that is why you
were assigned here.
A midwife...
I brought Jewish babies into the world.
You are never to touch
the things in here:
Soap, vitamins, painkillers,
yeast, quinine.
I have the only key to this cupboard.
However...
You will find that I often forget to lock up.
I hope you understand, 66685.
Oh...
Thank you, Lord!
He doesn't expect thanks for this.
It's warm.
I'm thankful for every
moment we can be together.
Yeah!
We can at least lie down tonight.
There has to be a plan, Corrie.
I won't be grateful for the lice.
God doesn't make mistakes.
How is it at the hospital?
Is it true your temperature has
to be over 104 to be admitted?
That's the rule.
There's a guard in the laundry.
You can get underwear for a price.
What does she want?
Bread rations.
Don't cut too much!
What do you want, hair or lice!?
You'll learn to love the little darlings.
The guards won't step foot in this lice pit.
Past the door, we can do anything.
Even lice!
6-6-7-2-7.
6-6-7-2-7!
6-6-7-2-7 is missing!!
♪ La, la, la, la, ♪
♪ la, la, la, la. ♪
Here!!!
Somebody overslept.
The loony.
Oh, Corrie...
We are in hell!
Why do they keep us so long?
To break us.
Betsie, look!
I was certain no one would die,
that we would all go home.
Those days on the train--
the Lord seemed to promise.
How could I have misunderstood?
Oh, dear Father, help me.
Don't let me listen to my voice
and think it is yours!
Oh Jesus...
Show me how to live in this place.
You too love him?
Here, put these in the mattress.
Not now! It's yeast,
and don't go spooning it around.
I can never get enough for everybody.
This method consisted of
painting only small dots
of pure colors on the canvas.
And color blending was achieved
by placing dots of different
colors next to each other.
And then from a distance the
two colors appeared blended
into one single new color.
Jesus Christ has made it possible
for us to have direct access.
There's a repeat at that point.
In the second movement?
That is a retardondo at
the end of the third bar.
♪ Da...
Da da-da ♪
♪Stand up for Jesus ♪
♪ Ye soldiers of the cross. ♪
♪ Lift high his royal banner... ♪
You're quite wrong,
the retardndo is later.
♪ ...It must not suffer loss ♪
Silence!!
Silence!!!
No room. No room! No room!!!
No room! No room!!
You find room.
Seig heil!
German whores...
We ran them through the hospital...
Infected.
What's with the yellow badge?
Race defiler...
Caught her with a Slavic laborer.
She's just a child.
Oh...
You've trod on my foot.
Oh!
Snell, snell.
Don't exert yourself, countess.
Oh, it's all I can carry.
Any more, and I'll have
to stop altogether.
I decide who stops!
Oh! Oh, oh! Oh!
Oh, oh!
Oh! Oh! Oh!
I decide who stops.
No!
No hate, Corrie...
No hate.
I want the most warm vest.
You owe 2 day's bread!!
I...I can pay you next week.
No!
Oh! Dumpkopff.
Jesus knows everything we feel.
He promised that when 2 or 3
get together in his name,
he would be there with them...
Even in Ravensbruck!
In our lives before,
we would have been
separated by so much;
but here, all that has
been stripped away.
And we see the truth:
Jesus in each one of us;
light in this darkness...
And we can praise Him together.
Father...
Bless the German people.
From your great storehouse of love,
forgive them for Jesus' sake.
Do not hold this place to their charge,
forgive them, even before they know to ask.
I'll give you one.
Two--or else you don't want the scarf!
I'll give you one now, one tomorrow.
I'll find you.
Come on now, rub it!
Rub it in!
A whole transport of Poles
came in last night.
Vulture.
You should know.
I have an undervest.
Eyes front!
It is wool.
No!!
Two days' bread ration.
My comb.
I'll collect later.
Nothing for the comb.
Rub hard!
Rub it in.
Thank you.
Oh!...
The sky is so peaceful.
You politicals don't have
anything to do with trash.
Ah!
We are all trash.
I took it off a tray...
In the infirmary.
Oh!!
Aaaaah!
Aaaaahhh!
Continue--
continue!
Ooooohh!
I though you were smart.
Aaahhh!!
You called attention to
yourself in the line.
Imbecile!
Could you not wait until you
were back in the block?
Are you such a greedy fool?
You German cow!!!
Maybe I should have let them kill you.
You great... Lumbering...
Hun!!!
Maybe you'd like to go in the box.
Box!! No light, no water.
You will never do anything
that stupid again.
Never!
Oooooooohhhh...
Now I will...
I will dress your hand.
"Comfort the frightened,
help the weak,
be patient with everyone.
Do not repay evil for evil,
but always try to do good to one another.
Always rejoice.
Pray constantly,
give thanks in all circumstances,
for this is the will of
God in Jesus Christ.
And to the mindless,
the words sound so comforting.
In this place it's mockery!
God didn't make this place...
Men did!
But He has power...
Surely He could stop them.
Unless, of course,
He's a sadist.
No! He's love, all love.
Then he's impotent.
You can't have it both ways, my dear!
You see what's around you.
We see another world,
just as real...
Our life with God.
Every day it gets deeper and stronger.
You think the two can't
exist side by side,
but we know they do!
We live them both!
It's enough knowing that
we're so much dung,
moving from nothing to nothing.
But you must believe your God
smells that stench from those chimneys
and refuses to do anything!
If only...
you could know his love.
I am Maria Wrochek...
First violinist of the
Warsaw Symphony Orchestra.
Did your God will this?
We cannot answer.
All I can say is that the
same God you are accusing
came and lived in the midst of our world.
He was beaten...
And He was mocked
and He died on a cross.
And He did it for love...
for us.
And why do you think
your God of love sent you here?
To obey Him...
If you know Him...
You don't have to know why.
First you take the juice of four oranges,
and a half a pint of cream,
and a cup of sugar.
I only use 3/4 of a cup.
You should use a full cup.
Then you put the peels
aside for grating,
and you whip the cream.
What kind of cook are you?
You forgot the eggs.
Do your own recipe, then.
We need more sand.
Corrie...
Don't shut me out...
Please.
You know you can only
give it to Jesus.
Do you think I haven't prayed?
But I hate them.
I hate every Nazi in this place!
We can't be more than what we are.
Only Jesus can free us from ourselves;
from whatever happens.
Sister...
You can't protect me.
You mustn't try.
Lord...
I cannot let go of it.
Take this hate...
Out of my life
and put your love in its place.
Jesus, there are many
things I do not understand.
Do not let me go mad...
poking about on my own.
You know what I am.
Saviour...
Hide me in the center of your will.
How long?
Four months.
What's it to you?
Child...
You would like to see me cry, wouldn't you?
Then you could mother me.
I only want to help.
What difference would it make?
Everything dies here.
Kraut! A lousy little whore!
We need vitamins and all
the calcium you can get.
You are so damned naive.
Two years older--
she'd be standing over you with a whip!
It's a baby, Katje, a new life!
I am not your personal Red Cross!
I can never get enough for
you, and her, and Betsie too!
What are you doing!?
Nothing! I was just...
I said "what were you doing?"
We have a pregnancy in 28.
A kid of 18.
She's...
I do not want to know!
All pregnancies are
transferred to experimental.
Yeast, B vitamins.
It'll help keep your soup down.
We even have a midwife.
Group 5 of 100 women,
report to the inspector.
Prisoner 146723
report to administration
for processing.
All this German slop has
to be good for something.
German papers, thick...
Like German heads!
It's a lot of hot air!
The yanks are halfway to the Rhine.
Oh!
So...
We'll put some hot air
between you and the wind.
Katje, thank you!
It's funny about you two.
Oh, well tell us...
We need a laugh!
You're always talking about love.
I bet neither of you ever had a man.
We had boyfriends.
Did you love your baby's father?
I was hungry.
He was nice to me.
I feel so strange.
I hurt!
I can't.
Well, try.
It goes like wood.
Oh, I am so weak!
Thank God--
He is strong.
Katje, Katje!
Betsie, try...
Please try.
Yeah.
Oh...
You know, Corrie,
we're...
we're going to be free!
Before the new year--
both of us.
Both of us?
The Lord showed me...
In a dream.
You'll see!
I'm not going to die, Corrie.
Oh...
No.
Far enough.
Leave her there.
Oh, please.
Leave her!!
All prisoners report to the Lagerstrasse.
Oh!
Ah!!
Please let me stay with her.
Roll call!!
Block 41...
Dismissed.
Block 28...
Block 33...
Dismissed.
Block 35...
Betsie!!
The prisoner is being transferred
to the hospital.
Prisoner 66730 requests permission
to accompany her sister.
What is the count?
Block 20: 4 dead.
Block 21: 3 dead.
Block 22: 6 dead.
Go on!
Block 23: Clear.
There should be more;
Count again.
Betsie!
Sister!
Thank Him, Corrie.
Thank the Lord...
For all He has done for us here.
Oh, you'll be warm soon.
Together...
You and I...
Always together.
Yeah!
Water.
Could I sleep here?
Just tonight?
It's so cold.
This way we would have 2 blankets.
If God loved Betsie so much...
Why?
Suffering does not mean
that God has stopped loving us.
Sometimes...
We have to accept things
we do not understand.
I love Betsie...
And I love you!
This is the sister.
Corrie...
You must look...
Otherwise, you'll never know.
She's beautiful.
Betsie!
We shall do
a great many things for others.
And we must go everywhere.
We must tell people
that no pit is so deep...
That he is not deeper still.
They will believe us...
because we were here.
Betsie talked about heaven
like she had already been there.
Yeah!
No one would wish her back.
Read for Betsie.
Read for all of us.
"For we know that our earthly bodies,
those we have now,
which will die--
must be changed for
our heavenly bodies,
which will not die...
But live forever.
Then the scripture will be fulfilled:
Death is swallowed up in victory."
So my dear ones...
Since future victory is sure,
be strong, and steady...
Always abounding in the work of the Lord.
For we know that our labor in the Lord
is not in vain...
As it would be if there
were no resurrection.
And this is the good news:
That Christ died for our sins
according to the scriptures.
And that He Rose again,
just as the prophets had said.
For God so loved the world that
He gave His only begotten son,
that anyone who believes
in Him shall not die...
But has eternal life!
Halt!
Achtung!
The following prisoners
will come forward
and stand by for selection and pickup:
6-6-7-0-0,
6-5-4-0-6,
6-6-7-1-8,
6-6-6-9-4...
No! She cannot walk!
Bring her!!
7-8-9-9-2.
Died last night!
6-6-7-3-0.
Corrie...
What you said, I want it--
I want him.
Then ask.
I don't know what to ask for.
He knows...
Just ask!
...7-4-2-8-1.
7-6-0-3-1.
Papa...
Sleep well, Corrie.
Papa?
Yes, Corrie.
What is it like to die?
When you and I go to Amsterdam,
when do I give you your ticket?
Just before we get on the train.
So with death.
When the time comes,
our wise Heavenly Father
will give you all the strength you need.
Prisoner 66730,
Ten Boom, Cornelia.
Sentence completed,
21st, 12, 44.
Sign.
What is it?
Prisoner certifies that all treatment
received during her imprisonment
has been adequate and humane
and that no accidents,
illnesses, or injuries have occurred.
Sign.
Kommen zie fraulien,
kommen zie!
You know, Corrie,
we are going to be free
before the new year.
We will...
I know it!
Years later it was learned
my release came through
a clerical error.
What some might call a "mistake."
Not long after I was set free,
women my age were put to death.
Yes...
I am Corrie Ten Boom,
in my 80s now.
Some questions remain,
but they are not to be feared.
Our Heavenly Father holds
all things in His hands,
even our questions.
As for myself,
in the years since Ravensbruck,
the Lord has sent me to some 60 countries.
And I have told to
anyone who would listen:
"No pit is so deep...
That He is not deeper still."
With Jesus...
Even in our darkest moments,
the best remains...
And the very best is yet to be!
I promised my sister I would tell it...
And I tell you!